Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is בבא קמא Bava
Kamma פ"ח, peh-chet, בבא קמא Bava Kamma 88. We pick up on
the last two lines of פ"ז עמוד ב, peh-zayin amud-bet, last word
on the line of the third line from the bottom. And we're
in the middle of an issue here, question about when a man's
daughter is injured, whether he collects the money for the injury or
not, and in the גמרא, Gemara, in the end the גמרא Gemara
sort of came to the position that basically he would only collect
the שבת, shevet, the loss of her
labor for the time that she was under age because he could
sell her as a slave for that time. All right, and then
the גמרא Gemara says like this, and we really should have read
these last two lines yesterday because just a few lines to finish
up the סוגיא. sugya. וכן אמר ריש לקיש, V'chein amar Reish Lakish,
and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish similarly said לא זכתה תורה לאב אלא
שבח נעורים בלבד. lo zachata Torah l'av ela shevach neurim bilvad. The
תורה Torah only gave the father the normal שבח נעורים, shevach neurim,
which is the right to marry her, to sell her as a
slave if she's under age, rabbinically if she finds a מציאה, metziah,
but not payments for the injury. Again, with the possible exception of
the שבת, shevet, but basically not payments for the injury. ורבי יוחנן
אמר, V'Rabbi Yochanan amar, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says אפילו פציעה, afilu
ptziah, even a wound, even if he didn't do any type of
serious injury, just you know, if he, not he, excuse me, even
if somebody else didn't do any type of serious injury, you know,
gave her a hit, made her black and blue, the father would
still collect. So the גמרא Gemara says פציעה סלקא דעתך? ptziah salka
daatach? Do you think for just a פציעה ptziah like how did
that actually, you know, like what payment is there for that? I
mean, I guess there could be בושת boshet or whatever, but why
would the father, you know, be entitled to that? אפילו רבי אלעזר
לא קמיבעיא ליה אלא חבלה דאפחתה מכספא. Afilu Rabbi Elazar lo qamibaya
lei ela chavala d'afchtah mikaspa. Even רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar's question, which
started this whole סוגיא, sugya, was a real type of a, you
know, injury that now she's worth less, like if he were to
try to sell her as a slave or if he were to
try to marry her off, you know, and there we can have
that whole discussion about does he actually collect or not. But why
should he סתם stam collect for some type of a wound that's
not going to impact his ability to make money for her when
he marries her off or when he, you know, when he sells
her? So the גמרא Gemara says אבל פציעה דלא אפחתה מכספא, aval
ptziah d'lo afchtah mikaspa, but a simple wound that's not making her
worth less or her money, her value is not worth less, לא
קמיבעיא ליה, lo qamibaya lei, that wasn't his question. אמר רבי יוסי
בר חנינא שפצע בפניה ואפחתה מכספא. Amar Rabbi Yose bar Chanina shepatza
b'faneha v'afchtah mikaspa. No, somebody hit her in the face and, you
know, and now even though it's not a permanent injury, now it
affected his ability to marry her off, you know, and maybe marry
her off at this time, maybe it's going to be take a
long time to heal, maybe it's a scar, and you know, and
therefore she won't be as attractive. So that's going to affect his
ability to collect for her. So all of this is, of course,
very disturbing in terms of the whole reality of the father treating
his daughter like goods and marrying her off and getting money for
marrying her off or selling her and so on. But what it
also shows, so I, you know, there's just whatever, that's obviously nothing
to say about that very deeply, deeply disturbing social reality. But what
it also shows is that the idea that the father would collect
seems to be from this גמרא Gemara not, you know, we basically
rejected it that the father wouldn't collect it, maybe some of the
issue for her labor. But here, but when the גמרא Gemara asks
he would collect, you know, the thinking was, oh, so what, even
if for her צער, tzaar, even for her suffering, even for her
embarrassment, like should we just assume that any money that comes through
the girl the father pockets? And it sounded like that a little
bit, that on the side that the father would collect, it would
be for any payments that would be going to her. Here, the
גמרא Gemara makes it sound that no, our whole question was about
something that actually impacted the father's pocketbook. That now because of her
injury, you know, he's not going to be able to sell her
as a, you know, for the, his ability to sell her and
get money for קידושין kiddushin or sell her for a slave, that
will be less money. And therefore, because he's going to lose that,
maybe he should actually the money for that should go to him.
So now the, at least the scope of the question of the
גמרא Gemara now makes more sense, that general assumption is pain, suffering,
embarrassment, you know, all of that the girl gets. The slight loss
of wages, you know, in terms of actually being laid up in
the hospital, you know, that you actually can't work, you know, that
would go to the father because that actually is like something that
he could sell. And the question is the fact that he could,
you know, sell her for less as a, because of the injury,
not the actual direct payment for the loss of wages, but the
injury which also impacts the fact that he could sell her for
less as a slave or as a bride, you know, should he
get that because that affects ultimately, you know, what he could sell
her for? Or do we say since he doesn't have the right
to do the injury, he also doesn't collect for the injury? So
the scope of the question of the גמרא Gemara now makes more
sense. Okay, we are done with that סוגיא sugya and now we
continue with the next. החובל בעבד כנעני של אחרים חייב. Hachovel b'eved
knaani shel acheirim chayav.
So this is the משנה, mishna, if someone... If somebody damages another
person's Canaanite slave, that's considered their property, then you pay and you
pay the full amount to the master.
But רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you do not pay for בושת
Boshet because there's no בושת Boshet for slaves. And if you remember,
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda also sort of categorically excluded a blind person
from liability for בושת Boshet the way the גמרא Gemara understood it.
And here רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is going to categorically exclude a
slave. And that led to all these discussions of other ways for
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda a blind person was categorically excluded from a
range of מצוות. Mitzvot. Here we're going to have something very similar.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda categorically excludes a slave from collecting בושת Boshet
or בושת Boshet being paid on account of a slave paid to
the master. And then the question is going to be what is
the scope that does a similar range of areas that רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda also categorically excludes a slave from different sort of מצוות
Mitzvot and liabilities or so on. Let's take a look. Okay, החובל
בעבד כנעני של אחר. Hachovel b'Eved K'naani shel acher. מאי טעמא דרבי
יהודה? Mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Yehuda? What's the reason of רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda that you do not pay בושת Boshet for injuring a slave
to the master? אמר קרא, Amar kra, the פסוק Pasuk says, כי
ינצו אנשים יחדיו איש ואחיו. Ki yinatzu anashim yachdav ish v'achiv. Okay,
if people fight and then the end of the פסוק Pasuk is
that a woman to defend her husband sticks out her hand and
grabs another person by his genitals, and it says cut off her
hand. And anyway, from there somehow חז"ל Chazal understand that there's an
obligation of בושת. Boshet. So the חיוב Chiyuv of בושת Boshet starts
by two people, איש ואחיו, Ish v'achiv, fighting with one another.
A man and his brother. יצא עבד, Yatza Eved, so איש ואחיו,
Ish v'achiv, במי שיש לו אחוה, B'mi sheyeish lo achvah,
somebody who has brotherhood. יצא עבד שאין לו אחוה, Yatza Eved she-ein
lo achvah,
to exclude a slave that does not have brotherhood. So what does
it mean that a slave doesn't have brotherhood? So a couple of
things. If you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, עם ישראל
שאינו בא בקהל. Im Yisrael she-eino ba b'kahal. He can't marry a
Jew, he's not considered to be part of that sort of community.
If that were true, you could ask how about a ממזר? Mamzer?
Should a ממזר Mamzer not also not have בושת Boshet because he
can't marry בקהל? B'kahal? So in the side it gives another answer.
עבד אין לו אחוה שמותר באחותו ובאשת אחיו. Eved ein lo achvah
shemutar ba-achoto u-v'eishet achiv. There's not considered to be any family relationships
with a slave. A slave can actually marry his sister. Slave is
not considered to be because חז"ל Chazal understood, different than non-Jews. Non-Jews
there's שבע מצוות בני נח, Sheva Mitzvot B'nei Noach, can't marry their
sister. But slaves fundamentally חז"ל Chazal understood that the whole family structure
speaks to the reality,
even though the תורה Torah recognizes that when a person is a
Hebrew slave, he has a wife and kids at the time and
so on. But for a non-Jewish slave, it does not sort of
see a family structure at all. And therefore, there's no sense of
family relations. There's no אחוה. Achvah. If you look at תוספות, Tosafot,
תוספות Tosafot says, פירש אין יוצאי חלציו קרויים אחים. Peirush ein yotzei
chalatzav k'ruyim achim.
A similar point except going laterally rather than horizontally, that his children
are not considered brothers to one another. His children aren't related to
him and not related to one another. So a slave that is
not in this category of family is not in בושת. Boshet. Exactly
what that means is that like a גזירת הכתוב, G'zeirat Hakatuve, does
that somehow mean that בושת Boshet only can occur amongst people seen
of sort of of a similar type of a status? But it's
not saying he's not equal status to ישראל, Yisrael, it's saying he
doesn't
have family. So does that mean if you don't have family, you
don't have any sense of community? And if you don't have any
community, therefore בושת Boshet is something that has to do with sort
of public embarrassment? Not exactly clear. But anyway, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
excludes a slave. ורבנן, V'Rabbanan, what would the Rabbis say back? אחיו
הוא במצוות. Achiv hu b'mitzvot. No,
he still is your brother in מצוות. Mitzvot. It might be that
there's not any sort of family structure
recognized, but nevertheless a slave is obligated. A slave, you take a
slave, you dunk him in the מקוה, Mikvah, and he's obligated in
מצוות Mitzvot even as a man, even as a man equal to
a woman. And then if he gets freed, he becomes fully obligated
as a man if we're talking about a male slave. So he
has a חיוב מצוות Chiyuv mitzvot like other Jews and therefore he's
considered to be part of your religious community. Maybe not part of
a biological family he's not recognized, but he is recognized as part
of your religious community. Very fascinating המאירי, HaMeiri, very sort of radical
המאירי HaMeiri in a number of places that spoke about how if
non-Jews keep the practices of their religion and abide by sort of
the moral tenets of their religion, they might be considered אחיו במצוות
Achiv b'mitzvot to Jews in for certain areas of הלכה. Halacha. Quite,
quite fascinating. But here anyway within the normal realm of Jewish מצוות
Mitzvot and Jewish observance, he is part of our Jewish religious family.
אחיו הוא במצוות. Achiv hu b'mitzvot. אלא מעתה, Ella me'ata, says the
גמרא, Gemara, if רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is going to say a
slave isn't in the frame of word of אחיו, Achiv, לרבי יהודה
זוממי עבד לא יהרגו. L'Rabbi Yehuda zom'mei eved lo yeiharegu. If people
are עדים זוממים Eidim Zom'mim and trying to, they came to make
say a slave committed murder and they're found to be guilty, then
they shouldn't have to pay, or they shouldn't have to be put
to death. Why not? דכתיב ועשיתם לו כאשר זמם לעשות לאחיו. De-chtiv
v'asitem lo ka-asher zamam la'asot l'achiv. You should do to them like
they tried to do to their brother. And this slave isn't their
brother for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, *Rabbi Yehuda*. Again, the rabbis say
he's part of our מצוות mitzvos *mitzvos* community, our religious community. But
for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*, זוממים *zomemim* for a slave
should not be put to death. And the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* thinks
that that's absurd. And as תוספות Tosafot, *Tosafos* says, if that were
true, then you could never obligate a slave because then it would
be עד ed, שאתה יכול להזימו *ed she'ata yachol l'hazimo*. You could
never bring a slave to דין *din* through עדות edus? *eidus* because
the עדות *eidus* could never get, because it's not in the category
of עדים זוממים *edim zomemim*, then also it can never be, the
עדות *eidus* could never be accepted. And we know you accept עדות
*eidus* against slaves. So how does this work? So אמר רבא אמר
רב ששת אמר קרא *Amar Rava, Amar Rav Sheishes, amar kra*, the
verse says, ובערת הרע מקרבך *uvi'arta hara mikirbecha*, you should destroy the
evil from your midst. מכל מקום *Mikol makom*. That's a broader sense
of the punishment of עדים זוממים *edim zomemim*. You should read that
category of who gets punished for עדים זוממים *edim zomemim* in a
broader way, not in a narrower way. So yes, עדים זוממים *edim
zomemim* do apply even when they're testifying against a slave. אלא מעתה
Ella me’ata *Ella me'ata*, says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, if that's true,
לרבנן עבד eved יהא כשר kasher. למלכות *lerabbanan eved yehe kasher lemalchus*.
For the לרבנן *Rabbanan* that think a slave is considered amongst you
are, you know, our brother in מצוות *mitzvos*, in our religious community.
So the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* says מקרב אחיך תשים עליך מלך *mikerev
achecha tasi alecha melech*. From amongst your brethren you shall make a
king, from which the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* understands that a slave or
even a גר ger. *ger* also cannot be a king because it's
not, you know, our natural, naturally born sort of brother, biologically part
of our community. But according to the לרבנן *Rabbanan*, why don't we
just say they're part of our מצוות *mitzvos* community, our religious community?
אמרי Amri, *Amri*, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says back, ולטעמך *ultamaich*,
according to you, תקשה לך גר ger. לדברי הכל *tikshalach ger ledivrei
hakol*. Why don't you ask about the idea of a גר ger
*ger*? Right? Whether you say רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*'s reason
or the לרבנן *Rabbanan*'s reason, a גר Ger, *ger*, you know, even
for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* who has a narrower definition
of
אחיו *achiv*, so a
גר ger *ger* should be אחיו *achiv* even for רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda*. Why? Well, first of all, he can marry into Jews according
to that explanation of רש"י *Rashi*, or his children are related to
him once he converts even though after he converts his parents are
not related to him, but at least his children are related to
him. So a גר ger *ger* should be considered to be אחיו
*achiv* for everybody. He's in our מצוות *mitzvos* community, our religious community,
he has
relatives after he converts, so his children will be relatives. So why
not? So obviously, so yeah, you got a question, why are we
so exclusionary by מלכות *malchus* if אחיך *achecha* should allow us to
include a גר ger *ger* for everyone and an עבד eved *eved*
for the לרבנן *Rabbanan*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אלא *ella*,
what you must say, אמר קרא מקרב אחיך *amar kra mikerev achecha*.
The word מקרב *mikerev* from the midst of your brethren, ממובחר שבאחיך
*mimuvchar shebe'achecha*, your primary brethren, or, you know, the most choice. Again,
it's very difficult all this stratification and who's fundamental and who's marginal
in society. But anyway, this is the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Okay, so
therefore we define אחיך *achecha* by king extremely narrowly and a גר
ger, *ger* is excluded, an עבד eved, *eved* is excluded, anybody who's
not basically a naturally born Jew. Okay, so that's that explanation. אלא
מעתה *Ella me'ata*, fine. Okay, but now let's keep on going. לרבנן
יהא עבד eved. כשר לעדות kasher le-edus. *Lerabbanan, yehe eved kasher le'eidus*.
For the לרבנן *Rabbanan* again that say an עבד eved, *eved* is
considered to be, you know, in our religious community, then an עבד
eved *eved* be כשר *kasher* for עדות *eidus*. דכתיב והנה עד ed.
שקר העד שקר ענה באחיו *Dechtiv vehinei ed sheker ha'ed sheker ana
be'achiv*, similar to the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* we had before about עדים
זוממים *edim zomemim*. They testified falsely against their brethren. So you need
the idea of brethren. So for רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* we understand
that that excludes a slave. But for the לרבנן *Rabbanan* why should
a slave be excluded from עדות *eidus*? אמר עולא עדות לא מצית
אמרת *Amar Ulla, eidus lo matit amrat*. No,
you can't say a slave is good to testify. אתיא עדות בקל
וחומר מאשה *Asya eidus bekal vachomer me'isha*. Because a woman is excluded
from עדות *eidus*. If a woman is excluded, certainly a slave would
be excluded. All right, so you're right, you're not excluding it
from slave, that's not how you exclude slave, you exclude it from
the fact that a woman because it says שני האנשים *shenei ha'anashim*,
the two men, and from there we learn men and not women.
And if a woman is excluded, certainly a slave is excluded. But
the word brother would not by itself exclude slave. ומה אשה שהיא
ראויה לבוא בקהל *U'ma isha she'hi re'uya lavo b'kahal*, a woman can
marry a Jew, obviously, then there'd be no one for the men
to marry, פסולה לעדות *pesula le'eidus*, nevertheless she can't testify. עבד eved.
שאינו ראוי לבוא בקהל *Eved she'eino ra'uy lavo b'kahal*, a slave that
cannot marry a Jew, אינו דין שפסול לעדות *eino din shepasul le'eidus*,
certainly he should be considered, you know, cannot testify. Now, why, what
is the logical relation between those two? Who knows. But anyway, that's
the קל וחומר kva chomer. *kal vachomer* of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says back, no, מה לאשה שאינה ראויה
למילה *ma le'isha she'eino re'uya lemila*, תאמר בעבד שהוא ראוי למילה *tomar
b'eved she'hu ra'uy lemila*. Wait, one minute, how do you know that's
what it's about? Maybe it's about maleness. I mean, that's a very
interesting way for the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* to say this. A woman
is not in the מצווה *mitzvah* of מילה *mila*. A slave is
in the מצווה *mitzvah* of מילה *mila*. So maybe that's what's important
about testimony. Pure maleness is what's important about testimony. קטן יוכיח *Katan
yochiach*. No, I'll prove it by a minor, שישנו ב... *sheyeshno b...*
He has מילה *milah*, he's a male, ופסול לעדות *upasul ledus*, he
can't testify. So you see, testifying is not about maleness. And nevertheless,
a woman is excluded, and therefore a slave should be excluded. No,
מה לקטן שאינו במצוות *Mah lekatan she'eino bemitzvot*. A קטן *katan* is
not yet obligated in מצוות *mitzvos*. A slave is obligated in מצוות
*mitzvos*. תאמר בעבד שהוא במצוות *Tomar be'eved shehu bemitzvot*, a slave is.
So maybe it's about being obligated in מצוות *mitzvos* and that's enough.
No, אשה תוכיח *Ishah tochiach*, שישנה במצוות ופסולה לעדות *sheyeshnah bemitzvot upsulah
le'edus*. No, but a woman is obligated in מצוות *mitzvos* and she's
exempt, so meaning what you have here is, is that you can't
say being qualified for מצווה *mitzvah* for עדות *edus* is enough to
be obligated in מצוות *mitzvos* because a woman is not qualified for
עדות *edus*. You can't say it's enough to be a male because
a minor is not obligated. So you have to figure out what
is the common denominator of exclusion. So וחזר הדין *vechazar hadin*, it
goes back and forth. לא ראי זה כראי זה ולא ראי זה
כראי זה *Lo rei zeh kirei zeh velo rei zeh kirei zeh*.
The characteristics of one case are not like the characteristics of the
other case. הצד השווה שבהם *Hatzad hashaveh shebahen*, the common denominator of
those that are excluded from עדות *edus*, שכן אינם בכל המצוות *sheken
einam bechol hamitzvot*, that they're not in all מצוות *mitzvos*. Meaning a
minor
is not- what do you call it? Is not obligated in any
מצוות *mitzvos* yet, and a woman is not obligated in מצוות עשה
שהזמן גרמא *mitzvot aseh shehazman gerama*. ופסולים להעיד *upesulim leha'id*, and they
can't testify. אף אני אביא את העבד שאינו בכל המצוות ופסול להעיד
*Af ani avi es haeved she'eino bechol hamitzvot upasul leha'id*. So a
slave, even as a male slave, is obligated in מצוות *mitzvos* at
the level of a woman. So therefore he should also be excluded.
It seems that the common denominator is not fully obligated in מצוות
*mitzvos*. Okay, and that's how we exclude slaves, not because of the
issue of brother, but because of not fully obligated in מצוות *mitzvos*.
So the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says one minute, מה להצד השווה שבהם
שכן אינו איש *Mah lehatzad hashaveh shebahen sheken eino ish*. תאמר בעבד
שהוא איש *Tomar be'eved shehu ish*. Oh, we're still going to go
back to maleness, okay? But rather than calling it מילה *milah*, we're
going to call it an איש *ish*, a man. Okay? Not a
male, but a man. So maybe it's about being a man, and
a woman isn't a man and a minor isn't a man. It's
really interesting, you know, seeing like what is at the heart of
this idea of not explaining it but identifying what's at the heart
of this idea of exclusion from עדות *edus*.
So you can't say- so why should an עבד eved, *eved* be
excluded? He's a man. And for the rabbis, אחיו *achiv* is not
enough to exclude him. אלא תיתי מגזלן *Ela tesi migazlan*. Okay, how
about from a robber? מה לגזלן
*Mah legazlan*, okay, because he's excluded because of his- because of his
sin that makes him a רשע *rasha*. So no, מה לגזלן שכן
מעשיו גרמו לו *Mah legazlan sheken ma'asav garmu lo*. No, no, no,
that's separate. There he's פסול pasul, *pasul* because he brought it on
himself. He did something that shows that he's not fit to be
an עד eid *ed*. תאמר בעבד שאין מעשיו גרמו לו *Tomar be'eved
she'ein ma'asav garmu lo*. A slave didn't do any action that should
earn him this disqualification. אלא תיתי מגזלן וחד מהנך *Ela tesi migazlan
vechad mehanach*. Okay, but fine, but combine a slave plus a woman
or a slave plus a minor. So you- in order to find
the common denominator there, it can't be that it's enough to be
a man. And if we're assuming that there's only one principle- I
don't know why we assume there could only be one principle. Maybe
it has to be a man who didn't do an עבירה *aveirah*,
you know, and then you would still have a slave. But assuming
that it's got to be one principle, what's the common principle that
explains woman, minor, and גזלן gazlan, *gazlan*? The common principle is not
do- not fully- they're not fully obligated in מצוות *mitzvos*, not fully
doing the מצוות *mitzvos*. Okay, a גזלן *gazlan* isn't fully observant, he
violates, and a woman and a minor are not fully- are not
fully obligated. So therefore a slave also, it is still about מצוות
*mitzvos*. Some sense of not being fully in the category of fully
obligated, fully performing מצוות *mitzvos*. So since a slave is not- and
that explains גזלן *gazlan*, אשה *ishah*, and קטן *katan*, so that's not
bad, and therefore a slave would also be excluded. But not because
he is not your brother. Okay,
now, מר בריה דרבינא אמר *Mar brei deRavina amar*, now Mar the
son of Ravina says no, it's based on a different פסוק pasuk?
*pasuk*. אמר קרא *Amar kra*, the verse says לא יומתו אבות על
בנים lo yumsu avos al banim. *Lo yumtu avot al banim*, the,
you know, fathers shall not die for their sons, which is usually-
and- interpreted to say that a father shall not- well normally it
might mean the פשט *pshat* of the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* for the
sins of their sons, you don't visit it on the fathers, but
also it's understood to be that you can't testify against a relative.
The father cannot die for a testimony of the son. But he's
now going to interpret it in a different way. לא יומתו על
פי אבות avos, שאין להם חייס בנים banim *Lo yumtu al pi
avot she'ein lahem chiyus banim*. Nobody can die for the testimony of
fathers who are not related to their children. Okay, and that's a
slave. If a slave has a child, it's not considered his son,
there's no sense of family. So therefore that is excluding a slave.
You can't testify- you can't die based on the testimony of a
father that- who's not related to his children. דאי סלקא דעתך כדאמרינן
*De'isalka da'atcha kideamrinan*, if you think like we normally say, לא יומתו
אבות על בנים lo yumsu avos al banim, בעדות בנים banim. *lo
yumtu avot al banim be'edus banim*, that it just means that fathers
can't testify- can't die based on the testimony of sons, sons can't
testify against their fathers, ליכתוב רחמנא לא יומתו אבות avos על בניהם
al banechem. *lichtov Rachmana lo yumtu avot al bnehem*. It shouldn't have
said בנים Banim *banim* in the generic.
It should have said fathers can't die for their- their sons, not
sons in general, their sons. Their sons can't testify against them. מאי
בנים? banim Why does it say it in the more generic sons?
שמע מינה Shma mina to teach you not only is it about
you can't testify against a relative, but דלא יומתו על פי אבות
שאין להם חייס בנים. de-lo yumsu al pi avos she-ein lahem khiyus
banim. That somebody cannot die because of a father who does not-
would not be related to his children. And that would be for
a slave and that excludes an enslaved. אלא מעתה says the גמרא,
if that's how you're going to read the פסוק, maybe we can
exclude a גר. ger. ובנים לא יומתו על אבות. U’banim lo yumsu
al avos. So sons will not die for their fathers. So again,
that's normally read sons won't die because of the testimony of their
fathers. Fathers can't testify against their sons. Okay, again to exclude relatives.
הכא נמי, Hacha nami, but according to your read, let's read it
this way. לא יומתו על פי בנים שאין להם חייס אבות. Lo
yumsu al pi banim she-ein lahem khiyus avos. That somebody can't die
for the testimony of a child who's not related to his father.
What type of a child is not related to his father? A
גר. ger, אלא גר הכא נמי דפסול לעדות? Ella ger hacha nami
de-pasul l'eidus? And
that would lead you to the conclusion that a גר ger. would
be invalid to testify? But that is not our הלכה. halacha. אמרי,
the גמרא says no, הכי השתא, hachi hashta, what type of a
comparison is that? גר, ger, ניהא דאין לו חייס למעלה, niha de-ein
lo khiyus le-ma'la,
it's true he's not related to his father, so it's a בנים
banim that doesn't have אבות, avos but למטה יש לו חייס, le-mata
yesh lo khiyus, once he converts, he'll have children, he'll be related
to his children. So it's an אבות avos, that has בנים. banim,
לאפוקי עבד, L'apukei eved, אין לו חייס לא למעלה ולא למטה, ein
lo khiyus lo le-ma'la ve-lo le-mata,
which excludes a slave. A slave is not a father that has
relationship to his children or child that has relationship to his father.
Okay, so reading the פסוק this way, you can't testify for a
certain person who's not related to his father or his son, that
excludes a slave who's not related to either. It wouldn't exclude a
גר ger. who, while he's not related to his father, is related
to his son. אי סלקא דעתך גר פסול לעדות, Ee salka da'atach
ger pasul l'eidus, because if the תורה Torah wanted to invalidate a
גר ger for testimony, לכתוב רחמנא לא יומתו אבות על בניהם lichtov
rachmana lo yumsu avos al banechem לכידאמרין. le-chid'amrin.
There's a lot of סתמא stama here. Anyway, the גמרא should have
said a father- that a-
fathers shall not die for their sons, meaning to speak about the
idea of relatives, but not to be talking about a case of
not related to your children. That's- not related to your children is
unique by a slave. A גר ger is related to his children.
So if we really wanted to invalidate a גר, ger we would
not have spoken about not related to your children. We would have
said על בניהם. banechem That's about the testimony of children against their
parents. Okay, that would have- how that would have been said. לא
יומתו בעדות בנים. Lo yumsu be-eidus banim. Okay, let it say בניהם
banechem so it's only talking about testimony of children against parents. ונכתוב
רחמנא בנים לא יומתו על אבות. Ve-nichtov rachmana banim lo yumsu al
avos. And then let it say sons will not die על אבות.
al avos. דשמע מינה תרי. De-shma mina trei.
Now that would mean how are we reading it when it says
you know אבות avos and not אבותיהם? avoteichem? Where's reading it to
say that children who you
know don't- are not- are not related to their fathers, you know,
they can't testify. בנים who do not have אבות, avos they can't
testify. So if we just had בנים לא יומתו על אבות, banim
lo yumsu al avos, okay, that would have told me גר. ger
Because that would mean who are children that don't have fathers? Those
are גרים. gerim. And they can't testify. דשמע מינה תרתי, De-shma mina
tartei, and that would let you get two things. חדא לא יומתו
בנים בעדות אבות, Chada lo yumsu banim be-eidus avos,
because it's generic it would mean like we normally interpret, that they
can't die on the testimony of you know בנים can't die on
the testimony of their fathers. ואידך, V’idach, but because it didn't say
אבותיהם, avoteichem, לא יומתו על בנים שאין להם חייס אבות. lo yumsu
al banim she-ein lahem khiyus avos. Okay, that they wouldn't die based
on a- children that are not related to their father. Okay, so
meaning, if you wanted to exclude a גר, ger you shouldn't have
given me both cases without the בניהם beneihem, אבותיהם. avoteichem. You should
have- you shouldn't have given both cases, which would say you can't
testify- you can't accept the testimony of somebody not related to sons,
and you can't accept the testimony of somebody not related to his
father. You should have just said the latter case, you can't accept
the testimony of somebody not related to his father, and that would
have excluded the גר. ger. And now once I'm excluding גר, ger,
ועבד נפקא ליה בקל וחומר מגר, ve-eved nafka leh be-kva chomer mi-ger,
and I would have learned עבד eved from גר. ger ומה גר
דלמעלה הוא דאין לו חייס אבל למטה יש לו חייס פסול לעדות,
U-ma ger de-le-ma'la hu de-ein lo khiyus aval le-mata yesh lo khiyus
pasul l'eidus, if a גר ger who's not related to his father
but is related to his son and he's פסול, pasul so even
though he's פסול even though he is related downwards but because he's
not related upwards, עבד שאין לו חייס לא למעלה ולא למטה, eved
she-ein lo khiyus lo le-ma'la ve-lo le-mata, a slave who's not related
neither to his father or his son, אינו דין שהוא פסול לעדות,
eino din she-hu pasul l'eidus, certainly would be invalid. Now it's a
little funny it has to learn it out from a קל וחומר.
Why not just learn עבד eved, and גר ger from the same
פסוק? That's an easier way to say what the גמרא is saying.
So let's say it that way. Okay, if the תורה Torah really
wanted to exclude both גר ger. and עבד, eved it would have
only said בנים לא יומתו על אבות. banim lo yumsu al avos.
Right? אבות לא יומתו על בניהם, Avos lo yumsu al banechem,
which would have been speaking about testimony of relatives. ובנים לא יומתו
על אבות, U-banim lo yumsu al avos, you can't go ahead and
accept the testimony of children who are not related to their fathers.
Who are children not related to their fathers? fathers, both a גר
ger. and an עבד. eved, Okay, so if it really wanted to
exclude both גר ger. and עבד, eved it only would have used
the like non-possessive by בנים לא יומתו על אבות, Banim lo yumsu
al avos, so that would have excluded both of them. Okay, but
it didn't. It also said לא יומתו אבות על בנים. avos al
banim, Okay, and that part אבות על בנים, avos al banim a
father that doesn't have a son, that only applies to an עבד
eved and not to a
גר. ger אלא מדכתיב רחמנא לא יומתו אבות על בנים, Ella mideksiv
Rachmana lo yumsu avos al banim, but since it also wrote אבות
על בנים avos al banim and not בניהם, דמשמע לא יומתו על
פי אבות שאין להם יחוס בנים, demashma lo yumsu al pi avos
she-ein lahem yichus banim, that you can't die based on fathers that
don't have children, and who are fathers that aren't related to their
children? That's only an
עבד. eved, שמע מינה עבד שאין לו יחוס לא למעלה ולא למטה
הוא דפסול לעדות, Shema mina eved she-ein lo yichus lo lemala velo
lemata hu de-pasul le-edus, that case because it went out and said
עבד, eved, the shorter way of saying this is: if it would
have פסל pasal גר, ger then you would have known עבד eved
as well. But because it went out and said the category that
applies only to עבד, eved אבות לא יומתו על בנים, avos lo
yumsu al banim, fathers that are not related to their children, since
that is an only עבד eved category and it's invalidating that,
אבל גר כיון דיש לו יחוס למטה כשר לעדות, aval ger kivan
de-ish lo yichus lemata kasher le-edus, but a גר ger. because he
is related to his children, he is כשר לעדות. Okay, so how
do we exclude a גר for עדות? Either based on the idea
of, you know, the common denominator of woman, minor, and גזלן, or
because of this דרשה drasha of בנים and אבות and אבות and
בנים, and because that we're understanding saying that you have to have
a relationship either to your parents or to your children to be
an עד, and a גר is related neither to his father nor
to his sons, so therefore he cannot be an עד. Okay. וכי
תימא ליכתוב רחמנא בנים לא יומתו על אבותיהם למה לי דכתב רחמנא
בנים לא יומתו על אבות? V'chi teima lichtov Rachmana banim lo yumsu
al avoseihem lama li de-ksav Rachmana banim lo yumsu al avos? Once
that's true, that all he wanted to do was exclude an עבד,
eved? why did we therefore say
ובנים לא יומתו על אבות? u-banim lo yumsu al avos? Why not
say אבותיהם? avoseihem? בנים לא יומתו על אבות Banim lo yumsu al
avos seems to be excluding somebody not related to his father, seems
to be excluding a
גר. דמשמע לא יומתו על פי בנים שאין להם יחוס אבות. Demashma
lo yumsu al pi banim she-ein lahem yichus avos. Why did it
say it על לא יומתו בנים על אבות? al lo yumsu banim
al avos? That sounds like we're excluding a son that isn't related
to his father, it sounds like we're excluding a גר. If that's
not the actual הלכה, halacha, why did we say it?
איידי דכתב לא יומתו אבות על בנים כתב נמי ובנים לא יומתו
על אבות. Aidi de-ksav lo yumsu avos al banim ksav nami u-banim
lo yumsu al avos. Because the פסוק wanted to speak in parallel.
So once it said לא יומתו אבות על בנים, and אבות על
בנים excludes an עבד eved because an עבד eved isn't related to
his father, therefore it says ובנים לא יומתו על אבות, u-banim lo
yumsu al avos, but we didn't mean to exclude a גר. So
again, אבות לא יומתו על בנים avos lo yumsu al banim is
excluding somebody who does not is not related to his father, is
excluding an עבד, and therefore since the תורה Torah went out of
its way to exclude an עבד, we assume that a גר is
כשר. A גר is related to his father, not related to his
sons. And when it says ובנים לא יומתו על אבות, u-banim lo
yumsu al avos, that's only coming to that's just the language is
parallel but it's only coming to exclude testimony of a relative, not
coming to exclude a גר. Fine. Anyway, that's how we know that
a slave is פסול לעדות pasul le-edus even though דרבנן, derabbanan, slaves
would be in אחוה. achva. Now, it's worth looking at this at
one or two תוספותים Tosafotim here that are quite surprising or shocking,
interesting to at least interrogate how much will we exclude an עבד
from different areas according to רבי יהודה, who says an עבד isn't
in אחוה. achva. So look at the תוספות, Tosafos תוספות דכתיב כאשר
זמם לעשות לאחיו. Tosafot de-ksiv ka'asher zamam la'asos l'achiv. תימא דתקשי ליה
לרבי יהודה מריבית ואונאה וגונב נפש דבכולהו כתיב אחיו. Teima detikshei le-Rabbi
Yehuda mi-ribbis ve-ona'a ve-gonev nefesh deb-chulhu ksiv achiv. Are we going to
say that an עבד is not in the category of charging ריבית
ribbis and אונאה ona'a or, you know, stealing, kidnapping ובצדקה נמי כתיב
אחיך העני, u-vi-tzedaka nami ksiv achicha he-ani, your brother the poor person?
Are we supposed to think that you don't have an obligation
of צדקה tzedaka to an עבד? This is really an important question,
right? How much, you know, it's one thing saying an עבד is
חייב במצוות, chayav be-mitzvos, but how much is it sort of is
that part of the interpersonal obligations that apply to, you know, normal
fellow Jews? Okay, and צדקה tzedaka is a really good question, right,
in terms of that. It's one thing about not wronging them, how
about an obligation of צדקה? tzedaka? Would for רבי יהודה would he
exclude an עבד from that? ומיהו קצת משמע בפרק קמא דגיטין דאין
כל כך חובה ליתן צדקה לעבד. U-mihu kzat mashma be-perek kama de-Gittin
de-ein kol kach chova liten tzedaka le-eved. It sounds there maybe there's
a hint from there that maybe the obligation of צדקה tzedaka to
a slave is a little bit not the same as to a
fellow Jew. דאמר דרבי שמעון בן גמליאל סבר יכול עבד לומר לרבו
בשני בצורת או פרנסני או הוציאני לחירות היכא דחזי ליה אינשי מרחמי
עליה. De-amar de-Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel savar yachol eved lomar l'rabo bi-shnei
batzores o parneseni o hotzi-eni le-cheirus heicha de-chazei lei inshi merachamei alei.
Okay, that the גמרא actually whatever without going into the details, but
it's basically like it sounds like the slave is saying, you know,
if it's a type of famine, he can say to the master,
look, either feed me and if you can't afford to feed me
you have to free me because as a free man people will
give me more צדקה tzedaka than they will as a slave. Now,
that might talk about a social reality, people are more willing to
give צדקה tzedaka to a Jew than to a slave owned by
a Jew, but it doesn't really speak necessarily about the difference of
the level of חיוב. chiyuv. Okay. And here now he points out
so alright. וגנב נפש נמי לא מחייב בעבד אפילו רבנן דבני ישראל
כתיב v'gonev nefesh nami lo mechayeiv b'eved afilu Rabbanan d'Bnei Yisrael ktiv
and maybe you know what טאקע takeh when it comes to kidnapping
that might be limited to Jews even for the Rabbis because it
says בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. Okay? So ורבית ואונאה נמי אין כאן
לעבד בלא רבו v'ribis v'ona'ah nami ein kan l'eved belo rabo and
as far as רבית ribis and אונאה ona'ah are concerned he says
well how do you actually do רבית ribis and אונאה ona'ah for
a slave? Slave doesn't have his own money which is like a
technical point not really categorical. So he really raises a very important
question. You know once the רבנן Rabbanan are saying he is a
חיוב chiyuv then the גמרא is willing to say oh let him
be an עד you know and once רבי יהודה says he's not
a חיוב chiyuv תוספות is saying so how many things are you
going to exclude him from?
Okay. Alright so that's that. Let's take a look now in the
גמרא continued in the גמרא here bottom of פח עמוד א peh-ches
amud aleph two lines on the bottom חרש שוטה וקטן פגיעתן רעה
cheresh shoteh v'katan pegiyatan ra'ah you know bumping into or actually you
know having
a injury with a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh v'katan a conflict
with them is going to lead to trouble because for you because
they're going to be exempt anything they do to you and you're
going to be liable for anything you do to them. They're exempt
because they are not obligated in הלכות halachos and מצוות and so
on. Okay. אימיה דרב שמואל בר אבא מהגרוניא imeih d'Rav Shmuel bar
Abba m'Hagronia the mother of רב שמואל בר אבא Rav Shmuel bar
Abba from Hagronia הוי נסיבא ליה לרבי אבא havi nesiva leh l'Rabbi
Abba was married to רבי אבא. Rabbi Abba. Now that's a very
funny phrase. If
she is the mother of שמואל בר אבא Shmuel bar Abba then
presumably she's obviously married to רבי אבא. Rabbi Abba. Okay so some
want to explain that this means that actually her first husband was
אבא מהגרוניא Abba m'Hagronia and this is a different רבי אבא Rabbi
Abba and that actually works in the story as we're going to
see. So it's a little confusing but anyway let's assume that. So
this woman this mother of שמואל Shmuel is married now to a
somebody who is שמואל's Shmuel stepfather this רבי אבא. Rabbi Abba. הוי
נסיבא ליה לרבי אבא havi nesiva leh l'Rabbi Abba כתבינהו לנכסה לרב
שמואל בר אבא ברה. kasvinhu l'nechsa l'Rav Shmuel bar Abba breih. Okay
she signed over all of her property she wrote like
something maybe would take effect the moment before she died that it
should all be a gift to רב שמואל בר אבא Rav Shmuel
bar Abba her son. Now why did she do that? Because had
she not given over this gift she would have died her property
would have gone to her husband. Her husband would have died then
and it would have gotten distributed to his children not to his
stepson this רב שמואל Rav Shmuel assuming that we're going to assume
stepson. Even if it's the same רבי אבא Rabbi Abba it would
have divided equally among his sons and רב שמואל's Rav Shmuel mother
wanted her property to go only to her son not to his
you know his other brothers okay which might not have been her
children. Okay so for whatever reason it is she wrote over her
property to her son she was married to רבי אבא Rabbi Abba
that kept it away from רבי אבא Rabbi Abba and went straight
to her son. Okay and then she died. בתר דשכיבה basar d'shchiva
then she died after she died. Top of פח עמוד ב peh-ches
amud beis אזל רב שמואל בר אבא קמיה דרבי ירמיה בר אבא
azal Rav Shmuel bar Abba kameih d'Rabbi Yirmeya bar Abba רב
שמואל בר אבא Rav Shmuel bar Abba who was the one to
who was the recipient of the gift went in front of רבי
ירמיה בר אבא. Rabbi Yirmeya bar Abba. Okay רבי ירמיה בר אבא
Rabbi Yirmeya bar Abba now this is pretty funny right? Is this
his brother? Is this his stepbrother? How are you going to a
court case here? Isn't somebody here a relative and you're not allowed
to go to a court case? That never gets explored by the
גמרא. Alright maybe the facts weren't in debate and you didn't have
to really go to a בית דין beis din it was really
a question about halachically whether it worked or not but it's still
pretty funny if it's the same רבי אבא Rabbi Abba here but
we're going to bracket that that doesn't get discussed. Anyway he went
to רבי ירמיה. Rabbi Yirmeya. אוקמיה בנכסי okmeih b'nechsei
רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmeya said yeah that's your property your mother signed
it over to you before she died. אזל רבי אבא azal Rabbi
Abba so רבי אבא Rabbi Abba who was the you know the
woman's husband who died you know his father or his stepfather אמר
ליה מילתא קמיה דרבי הושעיא. amar leh milta kameih d'Rabbi Hoshaia. He
went and he told רבי הושעיא Rabbi Hoshaia look here's what happened
my wife wrote over her property to רב שמואל Rav Shmuel and
now she died does that work? Did רב שמואל Rav Shmuel get
it or should I be getting it? אזל רבי הושעיא אמר קמיה
דרבי יהודה azal Rabbi Hoshaia amar kameih d'Rabbi Yehuda so רבי הושעיא
Rabbi Hoshaia went and reported this to רבי יהודה what's the story
in that case? Okay does the property go to the son that
the mother wrote over? אמר ליה הכי אמר שמואל amar leh hachi
amar Shmuel you know what this is what שמואל Shmuel says not
the same as רב שמואל Rav Shmuel אבא's Abba okay anyway this
is what שמואל Shmuel says האישה שמכרה בנכסי מלוג בחיי בעלה ומתה
הבעל מוציא מיד הלקוחות. ha'isha she'machrah b'nichsei melog b'chayei ba'alah u'meisah haba'al
motzi miyad halakochos.
A woman who writes over property that's נכסי מלוג. nichsei melog. What's
נכסי מלוג? nichsei melog? נכסי מלוג nichsei melog is property that she
brings into the marriage she retains the title of but the husband
has the right to be אוכל פירות ochel peiros to get the
benefit from it. Okay so assuming that it's let's say a field
an orchard let's make it very literal he gets the right to
have all the apples of the orchard even though she retains the
title. Alright if it's let's say she brings in I don't know
an apartment building he gets the right to take all the rent
from the apartment building when they rent it out okay but she
retains the title. So the division is she has the קניין הגוף
kinyan haguf she owns the title he has the קניין הפירות kinyan
hapeiros he owns it for the benefit that comes from it. That's
the relationship of property נכסי מלוג nichsei melog that a woman brings
into the family and that... And that presumably was the property we're
talking about here that the mother of רב שמואל Rav Shmuel wrote
over to him. So he says, you know what, שמואל Shmuel says,
רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda's teacher שמואל, Shmuel, שמואל Shmuel says that if
a woman, exactly this case, אשה שמכרה ishah shemakhrah a woman sells
her נכסי מלוג nichsei milog while her husband is still alive, while
her husband still has the rights to the פירות, peyros, if her
husband sells the rights to the פירות peyros and she tried to
sell the title, okay, and then she dies, the husband can negate
the whole sale since he had the rights to the פירות, peyros,
she was not allowed to sell it without his okay. So therefore
that's what happens here, she essentially sold it or she gifted it
without her husband's okay, it does not take effect, because he has
rights as well, he has rights to the פירות. peyros. Okay, אמרו
קמיה דרבי ירמיה בר אבא. amru kameih deRabbi Yirmeyah bar Abba.
So they went and they said this fact to Rabbi Yirmeyah bar
Abba. Hey Rabbi Yirmeyah bar Abba, you said that this רב שמואל
בר אבא Rav Shmuel bar Abba would get gets the property. You
know that שמואל Shmuel actually says that the sale in such a
case is not good when a mother tried, when a wife tries
to sell property like that?
So אמר להו amar lehu he said back, אנא מתניתין ידענא. ana
matnitin yadana. It's very nice what you tell me in the name
of שמואל, Shmuel, I know a משנה. Mishnah. And a משנה Mishnah
says that such a thing like this does work. What's the
משנה? Mishnah? דתנן, detnan, we taught in a משנה. Mishnah. הכותב נכסיו
לבנו לאחר מותו. hakotev nekhasav livno leachar moto. A similar case of
קניין פירות kinyan peyros and קניין גוף. kinyan guf. A father writes
over to his son his property that his son will get after
the father dies. Okay, now the effect of that is, this is
yours, from today and after I die. What's the effect of that
if you write that language, it's you own this field, this apartment
building from today and after I die? So it says that means
that the son owns the title, that way the son will get
it when the father dies. But until the father dies, the father
has the rights to the פירות. peyros. Okay, so it's very similar.
The son has the title, the קניין הגוף, kinyan haguf, and the
father has the קניין פירות. kinyan peyros. So translating that, the son
is like the wife, owns the title, and the father is like
the husband, owns the קניין פירות. kinyan peyros. הכותב נכסיו לבנו לאחר
מותו, hakotev nekhasav livno leachar moto,
that the son should get it now and for when after he
died. הבן אינו יכול למכור מפני שהן ברשות אב. haben eino yakhol
limkor mipenei shehen bireshut av. The son can't sell his ownership, his
title, because the father has the rights to the פירות. peyros. האב
אינו יכול למכור מפני שהן כתובין לבן. haav eino yakhol limkor mipenei
shehen ketuvin laben.
The father can't write it, can't sell because it's written over to
the son, the son has the title. Okay, neither of them can
sell right now, can finalize the sale because each one has a
stake in it. So while they're both alive, the sale can't be
final. Okay. Now, מכר אב, makhar av, now the father let's say
he actually went out and he did sell it. So מכורין עד
שימות. mekhurin ad sheyamut. So what did he sell? He sold his
rights. His rights are the פירות. peyros. So he went ahead and
he sold his rights to the apartment building, let's use that, the
person he sold it to can collect the rent until the father
dies. Why? Because that was the father's rights in the apartment building.
The father had the right to the rent, to the פירות peyros
until the father died. So if he sold it to somebody, that
person gets the rent until the father dies. Once the father dies,
it all now goes to the son as was arranged. מכר הבן,
makhar haben, let's say the son sold his title in the apartment
building. אין ללוקח עד שימות אב. ein lalokeiach ad sheyamut av.
The purchaser doesn't get anything until the father dies. Okay, so because
it was a sale,
he sold the title, but the title didn't mean anything, the father
still had the קניין פירות. kinyan peyros. So the guy who buys
the title, he's not better off than the son, he doesn't get
anything until the father dies. Okay, but what does that משנה Mishnah
suggest? It suggests כי מית אב מיהא איתיה ללוקח, ki meit av
miha itei lalokeiach,
that when the father does die, okay, the purchaser, the guy who
purchased from the son, does get it. It sounds like the son's
title did transfer to the other person. The person doesn't get anything
out of it yet because the father has the פירות. peyros. But
once the father dies and his פירות peyros go away, his rights
go away, this person totally owns it. And that's exactly what happened
in our case. The mother gave it to
רב שמואל. Rav Shmuel. And therefore, it's going to now go to
him. The problem of course is that who died first? So let's
take a look. So כי מית אב מיהא איתיה ללוקח, ki meit
av miha itei lalokeiach, when the father does die the purchaser does,
and אף על גב דמית הבן בחיי האב, af al gav demeit
haben bechayei haav, even though the son died while the father was
still alive, דלא אתי לידי הבן, delo ati lidei haben, it didn't
come yet into the possession of the son. So again what is
this? The son sells the title to ראובן. Reuven. The father is
still alive. So ראובן Reuven doesn't get anything yet because the father
has פירות. peyros. And
that's going to be a reality as long as the father's alive.
The son dies. Okay, the son dies. ראובן Reuven still has title.
Then eventually the father dies. Now ראובן Reuven can take the פירות,
peyros, which basically means the son's sale of the title worked even
while the father was still alive and still had. Then eventually the
father dies. Now, ראובן Reuven can take the פירות, peiros, okay, which
basically means the son's sale of the title worked even while the
father was still alive and still held on to the פירות. peiros.
And that would be exactly like our case. The mother gifts it
to the son, the husband is still alive, he still has פירות,
peiros, that works. The mother dies, okay, so the son here still
has the title that his mother gave him. And once רבי אבא
Rabbi Abba dies and the פירות peiros his right to the פירות
peiros go away, the son would be able to use the פירות.
peiros. So what you see here is that the sale did transfer
even though the father even though in the case of the father
and the son, the father was around and he was still eating
the פירות, peiros, the sale did transfer. Like ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish,
and this goes like ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, דאמר de'amar who says,
לא שנא מת הבן בחיי אב דלא אתו לידי הבן, lo shna
mes haben b'chayei av de lo atu lidei haben, it doesn't matter
if the son dies first while the father was alive that the
son never fully got the property yet, he only had the title
without the פירות, peiros, לא שנא מת אב בחיי הבן, lo shna
mes av b'chayei haben,
and it wouldn't matter if the father died first obviously that's the
better case when the son was alive, דאתו לידי הבן d'atu lidei
haben that the son got full possession. So whether the son ever
got full possession or not in the case of a father or
son, it doesn't matter, קנה לוקח, kana lokeach,
the purchaser got the title that the son had. And when the
father eventually dies, the purchaser will get it all. Okay, and that
should be just like our case with the mother and the husband.
דאיתמר de'itmar because it was taught. Okay, what is this ריש לקיש?
Resh Lakish? Because we'll see it's a debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan and ריש לקיש. Resh Lakish. מכר הבן בחיי האב
ומת הבן בחיי האב. machar haben b'chayei av u'mes haben b'chayei av.
The son sells, you know, exactly our case.
Debate of how to understand this משנה Mishna about the son selling.
The son sold while the father was alive and the son died
first. Would that sale go through so the purchaser will get the
פירות peiros you know will get the whole thing once the father
dies? רבי יוחנן אמר לא קנה לוקח. Rabbi Yochanan amar lo kana
lokeach. No, the purchaser did not go through. For the son to
sell his title, he has to become in full possession. He cannot
sell his title while the father has קניין פירות. kinyan peiros. ריש
לקיש אמר קנה לוקח. Resh Lakish amar kana lokeach. No,
the sale did go through. He can sell just his title. רבי
יוחנן אמר לא קנה לוקח Rabbi Yochanan amar lo kana lokeach he
did not the purchaser did not get it, ראובן Reuven didn't get
it. אמרו לו כי תני מתניתין מכר הבן לא קנה לוקח עד
שימות האב amru lo ki tanni matnisin machar haben lo kana lokeach
ad she'yamus ha'av
when our משנה Mishna says that when the son sells it, the
purchaser you know will get it עד שימות ad she'yamus will get
it when the father dies. So yes, the משנה Mishna did allow
for a case that the ראובן Reuven if the son sells it
to ראובן, Reuven, ראובן Reuven gets it when the father dies. When
is that true? וכי מת אב איתא ללוקח v'chi mes av isa
l'lokeach and then when the father dies yes ראובן Reuven will get
it. When is that true in the משנה? Mishna? דלא מת הבן
בחיי האב delo mes haben b'chayei av
that the son didn't die first, that the father died first. So
the משנה Mishna says if the son sold it to ראובן, Reuven,
ראובן Reuven will get it when the father dies, that's only when
the father dies first. Because then the father died first, the son
came into full possession retroactively or whatever, the father was never there
to sort of you know that the fact that now it all
comes into the possession of the son allows that sale to take
place. Okay, דאתו לידי הבן. d'atu lidei haben. That in that case,
the father was out of the picture, the son got the rights
to the פירות peiros and then it all transferred to ראובן. Reuven.
So that works when the father gets out of the picture first.
דאתו לידי הבן. d'atu lidei haben. אבל מת הבן בחיי האב, aval
mes haben b'chayei av,
but if the son dies first, he sold the title to ראובן
Reuven and then he died first, דלא אתו לידי הבן, delo atu
lidei haben, he never got full possession of it, the son, כי
מת אב נמי לא ליתי ללוקח, ki mes av nami lo leisi
lokeach,
when the father dies, the son the purchaser is not going to
now get the פירות. peiros. Why? Because the son's sale of the
title when the father always retained control of the פירות, peiros, that
does not go through. Why not? אלמא קסבר alma kasavar and this
is the classic debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש,
Resh Lakish, קניין פירות כקניין הגוף דמי, kinyan peiros kekinyan haguf dami,
because the father's right to the פירות peiros makes the father considered
an owner. Okay, the son maybe doesn't mean the son isn't an
owner or at least the father's an equal owner. Because the father
has קניין פירות, kinyan peiros, he the son does not have the
ability to sell the title with the father you know you know
while the father is still present. So if the son's sale of
the title would ever go through, it would only be after if
the son was alive and the father died. Okay, but while the
father is still present, the son cannot sell the title. So if
the son goes sells dies first, nothing happens. That's what רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan says. וכי זבין לאו דידיה זבין v'chi zavin lav dideh
zavin
and therefore when the son is trying to sell and the father
is around and the father's always around when the son is alive,
the sale does not go through. ריש לקיש אמר Resh Lakish amar
and ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says no, קנה לוקח. kana lokeach. ראובן
Reuven did get it. כי תני מתניתין מכר הבן אין לוקח עד
שימות האב, ki tanni matnisin machar haben ein lokeach ad she'yamus ha'av,
when the משנה Mishna says that the purchaser ראובן Reuven will get
it once the father dies, וכי מת אב מיהא איתא ללוקח, v'chi
mes av mi'ia isa l'lokeach, and once the father dies ראובן Reuven
will get it, לא שנא לא מת הבן בחיי אב, lo shna
lo mes haben b'chayei av, לא שנא lo shna דאתו לידי הבן,
d'atu lidei haben, it doesn't matter if the father died first and
the son came into full possession while he was alive. מכר הבן
אם לוקח עד שימות האב muchar ha-ben im lokeach ad she-yamus ha-av
where the משנה mishna says that the purchaser ראובן Reuven will get
it once the father dies, כי מית אב מטיא לידיה דלוקח ki
meis av matya lidei d'lokeach and once the father dies ראובן Reuven
will get it. לא שנא לא מית הבן בחיי האב, lo shna
lo meis ha-ben b'chayei ha-av, לא שנא דאתא לידיה דבן, lo shna
d'ata lidei d'ben, it doesn't matter if the father died first and
the son got into full possession while he was alive, ולא שנא
מית הבן בחיי האב v'lo shna meis ha-ben b'chayei ha-av and it
doesn't matter if the son died first, ודלא אתא לידיה דבן u-d'lo
ata lidei d'ben that the son never became in full possession, even
if the son dies first, קני לוקח, kanei lokeach, ראובן Reuven gets
it. אלמא קסבר alma kasavar so we see that ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish is of the opinion קנין פירות לאו כקנין הגוף דמי kinyan
peiros lav k'kinyan ha-guf dami that the father's right to the פירות,
peiros, it does not make the father an owner. So although the
father has rights to the פירות, peiros, the son obtains full title
as owner and therefore the son can transfer the title to ראובן
Reuven even while the father's alive and that will be a good
transfer even if the son dies first. And that is exactly our
case. The mother transferred to her son רב שמואל Rav Shmuel even
though her husband with the קנין פירות kinyan peiros was alive and
therefore רב שמואל Rav Shmuel gets the title and he'll get it
all once once רבי אבא Rabbi Abba dies. Okay, so אלמא קסבר
קנין פירות לאו כקנין הגוף דמי alma kasavar kinyan peiros lav k'kinyan
ha-guf dami וכי מזבין דידיה מזבין v'ki mazbin didei mazbin and when
the son is selling he's selling his own thing. ואנן השתא v'anan
hashta now we here there's a lot of סתם stam in these
גמרות gemaras I don't know why. Okay, ואנן השתא v'anan hashta בין
רבי ירמיה בר אבא bein Rabbi Yirmiya bar Abba בין רב יהודה,
bein Rav Yehuda,
whether it's רבי ירמיה בר אבא Rabbi Yirmiya bar Abba the one
who made the ruling to give it to the son in this
case of the mother writing over a property, whether רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda who went and got a פסק psak from שמואל Shmuel that
seemed to be disagreeing, but we know that both of them כרבי
שמעון בן לקיש סבירא להו k'Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish sevira lehu that
they basically hold like ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that קנין פירות לאו
כקנין הגוף דמי. kinyan peiros lav k'kinyan ha-guf dami. That's just a
general principle we פסק'ן pasken like ריש לקיש Reish Lakish and therefore
everyone should agree that the mother can transfer title.
וקאמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא v'ka'amar Rabbi Yirmiya bar Abba and therefore
רבי ירמיה בר אבא Rabbi Yirmiya bar Abba by quoting this משנה
mishna is he essentially saying to רב יהודה Rav Yehuda who challenged
his ruling אי סלקא דעתך קנין פירות כקנין הגוף, ei salka deitach
kinyan peiros k'kinyan ha-guf,
if you think that קנין פירות kinyan peiros is כקנין הגוף, k'kinyan
ha-guf, right, that is the only way you're going to disagree with
my פסק. psak. Then כי מית אב ומית
הבן בחיי האב ki meis av u-meis ha-ben b'chayei ha-av
so if when the father dies and the son dies while the
father's alive אמאי איתא ללוקח amai isa l'lokeach
then why does, if you agree to this ruling of ריש לקיש,
Reish Lakish, the גמרא sort of a little being redundant repeating itself
in different ways. But if you agree to this ruling of
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that ראובן Reuven gets it even if the
son dies first, okay,
and you hold קנין פירות כקנין הגוף kinyan peiros k'kinyan ha-guf then
that doesn't make sense, why does that work? כי קא מזבין לאו
דידיה קא מזבין ki ka mazbin lav didei ka mazbin then the
sale shouldn't work because the son is not really the owner, the
guy the father with the קנין פירות kinyan peiros is the owner.
אלא לאו שמע מינה קנין פירות לאו כקנין הגוף דמי. ela lav
shma mina kinyan peiros lav k'kinyan ha-guf dami. Okay, that's like repeating
itself but it basically says look you know we all agree like
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that the sale of the son works, okay,
and that all makes sense based on the principle of קנין פירות
לאו כקנין הגוף דמי kinyan peiros lav k'kinyan ha-guf dami that the
father's does not have title and can't stop the son's sale and
we all hold like ריש לקיש Reish Lakish and we all hold
קנין פירות לאו כקנין הגוף דמי. kinyan peiros lav k'kinyan ha-guf dami.
So since we all hold that and we all hold that the
son's sale works then and the person with קנין פירות kinyan peiros
doesn't have right to stop it, then that should exactly be our
case with the mother giving it to her son.
אהדרוהו לקמיה דרב יהודה ahadruhu l'kamei d'Rav Yehuda they
they gave they told רב יהודה Rav Yehuda this counterchallenge. אמר להו
הכי אמר שמואל זו אינה דומה למשנתנו. amar lehu hachi amar Shmuel
zu eina doma l'mishnasenu. שמואל Shmuel said yeah but our case with
the mother and the husband and the son is not like that
משנה mishna of the father and the son and we will find
out tomorrow why it is not comparable to that case.